just because it's so depressing that
Stanley gave such a good talk about how
to have negative thoughts and the whole
morning was about how to have negative
thoughts and I kind of wanted to take
alarming break so I would like to go
back to that explanation about the
structure of the ACI courses because if
you're going to be an ACI teacher in the
back of your mind you should have a the
whole structure of the 18 foundation
courses okay so we did four of them
already and I would like to continue
with that maybe we do three or four more
courses what's some things we're talking
about in each course give me anything
one thing no I mean we're talking about
flow we're talking about why did the
course come before it and why did the
course come after it where is its
position in the flow what's something
else we talked about huh yeah we just
have the five Geshe topics and which of
the four ancient schools okay and then
you know we should talk about the
content a little bit what's another
thing that you I think you're not
remembering to say yeah great hmm you
are remembering yeah which great book
and most of those courses have a great
commentary okay so I don't just use the
ancient poem poem book all those books
are poems they're too deep they're too
difficult they need a explanation so I
took the best of the best and I'll
mention which commentary we use okay and
let's do that now just before I do that
I I was looking over the course and I
was thinking to me it's very interesting
the flow of the five grade topics in the
geschichte course which one comes first
you know do you start with Lois school
and then go to high school or do you
start with high school in case you die
halfway through the Geisha Court I mean
maybe you should start at the top and
and that dropout rate the death rate is
pretty high because 25 years you know so
naturally my class started with 60 young
men and we finished with four okay and
that's pretty typical we had four guess
she's graduated from my class okay and
the rest died or they left or they
couldn't do it okay so mmm so how do you
arrange the order what's the order okay
and it's a little bit unexpected and it
needs some explanation okay so here we
go and I put it in the document in your
manual okay by the way some of the
manual documents are not finished if
they don't look finished don't read them
because they're not and we're going to
try to finish the whole thing in three
terms in three trainings okay so by the
end of this year you will have all the
policies of ACI you will have all those
three courses you will have all this
information the whole structure blah
blah okay okay the first thing is the 75
pages text called jewel of realizations
by ya dictated by my trailer to his
secretary who took shorthand named a
Sangha yeah and if you know the dog
story from the lion stance you know how
it happened okay so our five great books
of Maitreya and this one we study first
okay what you can call by the way which
of the five topics yeah yeah perfection
of wisdom number four which is what
school no it's cool mine only lower
middle way okay no I'm in the way by the
way the Tsongas books are also mine
domain so that's a not a terrible answer
but okay so we studied that and the way
I described it you know it's 27 years
since I wrote these courses and
I kind of understood a way to describe
the perfection of wisdom scriptures okay
meaning the lower middle way scriptures
and they are a vast encyclopedia of all
Mahayana all Bodhisattva teachings are
there except yeah except a correct
totally correct presentation of
emptiness everything else in there is
amazing it's similar to our be Dharma
okay I'll be Dharma is like all the
foundation stuff you need to know
hundreds of ideas okay and lower-middle
way the jewel of realizations by the
written by the next buddha which is a
pretty good source and everyone agrees
he's already a buddha by the way he's
just hanging out and he's waiting until
people have enough seeds for him to come
or to recognize him so and he's close
okay it's coming everything's closed so
anyway that body of literature we spent
twelve years on it okay the first twelve
years so that's the first thing you
study in the monastery seventy five
pages you memorize it normally memorize
it before you're 15 and and it's cute
the kids go out on the you we have
twelve colleges right and every night
around this time they go out on the
balcony front porch and then then I
think a number D
no journey and they have no idea what
they're saying and it's cute and they're
trying to do it louder than the kids in
the next house so the monastery
you can't take a nap at that time
because the whole monastery there's 15
your kids screaming the obese time
Alencar you know it's kind of irritating
actually but it's a custom it's a custom
when you recite something like a mantra
you should do it loud enough for the
spirits to hear the spirits in the room
so it's a it's a tradition to not to
mumble your mantras like say them pretty
clearly so all the spirits in the room
can hear and I guess that's the theory
of the kids screaming is to keep the
monks awake the other monks okay so
anyway twelve years there and then after
that what makes logic I mean what's the
logical after that
let's fix their teaching on emptiness so
you spend four years on higher middle
way okay so that's a year number
thirteen to year number 16 of the gushie
course you spend four years basically
fixing the emptiness teachings
technically you are studying which book
yeah entering the middle way by
chandrakirti which is a great commentary
on Nagarjuna the Guardian is wisdom
okay and these books have associated
monastic text books okay they have the
commentaries that we use are huge okay
for the first twelve years it's about I
don't know four thousand pages of
commentaries by one author okay so each
monastery has their own monastery
commentary and normally it's two it's
two different commentaries one is called
Chi didn't say children children means
overview of the whole lower middle way
all the topics and then torture say
touch-a touch-a means analysis and both
books are always written in debate style
okay it's always two guys arguing
okay and that gets the student ready
okay so we actually don't study we study
the first 12 years based on eight books
from our monastery and big huge books
okay and then when we reach the second
topic which is higher middle way called
middle way okay we spent four years on
that and again there's a children and
there's a toucher
there's an overview and there's a dig
dig into it okay and those are
incredibly beautiful books we should
translate those two when we have time
okay incredibly beautiful books okay
and there are Indian commentaries to
each of them too and we use those for
middle way aside from the two monastic
textbooks what do you think we use
some coppice gumbo lobster okay so if
you're if you're a good student if
you're hardcore you're not you don't
just study the two monastic text books
which are about 2,000 pages but you
throw in some couples explanation
emptiness some couples explanation
chandrakirti which is called
illumination of the true thought what
did what did Nagato not really mean what
did chandrakirti really mean okay so
that's in our translation team we're
transcending that we just reached
halfway it took five years it's 750
pages so far okay so it will be about
1,500 2,000 pages when we finish in five
years okay and that's on coppice
ultimate commentary sometimes most the
time there's not time to study it
carefully so when I got to this subject
I requested special teachings from my
super scripture teacher which is Geshe
tipped invention I guess it's a picture
here and we spent eight years on it
and we started with four or five of my
friends and they all dropped off so I
don't know for me it was kind of cool
because I had an hour a day with the
greatest master and Sarah and that's
pretty cool and he's an incredible
teacher so okay so that's middle way
then we spent two years on vinaya two
years on vinaya okay year number 17 and
year number 18 are spent on vinaya vowed
morality ethics who's the main book
Vinaya Sutra which is not a Sutra it's
written by a human being called guna
papa okay and so we study it from guna
papa and again every monastery has their
own commentary and if you're interested
I mean I I enjoy talking about this
stuff it's probably boring to you but
anyway I don't care I don't get to talk
about it very much usually there's a
dome say dome so dog means
a summary of all the Vinaya as a pump
and you memorize it okay you memorize it
so Alison is translating one of those
she's chanting the shortest possible one
and a commentary but usually they're a
little bit longer and and you memorize
it okay so and if you really want to go
into it there are incredible
commentaries Jean Smith turned me on to
one which is Lord relaxing which is a
little-known author he's not very famous
but his commentary is the best and I
started to translate it here I worked on
it for about five years with somebody
they quit and they took all the
recordings from there yeah okay you're
not gonna do that right okay so anyway
this is vinaya now doesn't a question
come in your mind when I tell you you
don't study vinaya until were year 17
yeah me what else months doing you know
I mean they didn't study their vows and
you gang up to assume gnam 253 bells for
fully ordained monk
simcha 2 - Tehillim 364 for full nun why
they spent seven sixteen years in the
monster before they learn their vows and
this brings up another detail of the
gushie course that i should mention and
that's the the role of your Kagan the
role of your Jurgen or your Toyama ok
Garrigan means the house teacher the
college teacher who's kind of a
babysitter
you know they teach the kids to put
their robes on and they watch the kids
when we started the monastery we were
all refugees and it was all the kids in
the same room and they all had sores on
them we didn't have enough food and they
would spread the kids would touch each
other and they would spread and
everybody had these huge open wounds on
them and
so the housemothers job getting Lothar
who's been a housemother for probably
500 months so you should thank him he
takes care of them he feeds it's his job
to feed them and to find the money and
to get them clothing okay that's his job
and to make them monks and normally it's
that person in your life so it's kind of
an addition to the gushy course they
tell you you're you're monks vows by
personal experience you seen I mean yes
so when you break a vow they say hey
that's one of the 253 don't do that and
then that's how you learn your vows in
the monastery okay they might not sit
down with you and teach you your vows my
teacher did okay he used their Tibetan
commentary called
halt we caught it so now I say so now he
wrote a 2,000 page commentary on the
vows both monks and nuns incredible
extraordinary he's before it's on copper
so we do study other traditions he's a
cog you okay and it's an incredible
commentary and we use it every I still
use it almost daily when I'm teaching
vinaya okay
it's extraordinary so we will follow
this commentary so I did get training on
my vows as soon as I became a monk but I
was already 30 so I was lucky because I
had a chance to do all the bad things
before that so I did everything you know
really so I think it's maybe a you know
in the old days you didn't become mom
till you're 30 like I tell people like
that they didn't become a monk till
they're 30
they didn't take 4 vows a lot of them
studied Tantra before they became a
4-month so it used to be we wanted to
watch you longer we wanted to watch you
it was a kind of a big honor to be among
and oftentimes you did it later in your
life okay so the answer to the question
is before you reach the 17th year of the
Geshe course your house teacher has
taught you all the vows by telling you
what not to do when you do it ok and in
this kind of organic way
although young monks learn their vows
you know like like for example I'm not
allowed to take my robes off I can't
drop my robes and step over them that's
against the vows I have to untie it and
put it over my head and I cannot step
over the rope you know and it's in to
see the many rules like that and you
can't really write it in a book you know
if your teacher hits you once with the
rosary you'll you memorized it okay got
it
so that's where every night then you get
to you're 17 and you learn the ancient
sources and you learn the ancient
languages what's a ling she the original
incident so this is a very very
important idea in the running of
organizations like Diamond Mountain or
like ACI okay
Leng she means somebody screwed up
somebody screwed up for example
originally Buddhists were allowed to
drink alcohol okay
when the Buddha first started to teach
we were allowed to drink alcohol then
there was a lengthy what's it mean
someone got drunk and caused trouble I
don't remember what it was but you can
Stallions and because of John's database
you can search Leng she next to alcohol
and you will search a million pages in
less than 10 seconds so if you learn the
scriptures with John Brady's database if
you ask me right now well what was the
incident what happened I can find it in
about 10 seconds I can search a million
pages in about 10 seconds so actually
the course is that you're getting are in
many ways the information is more
precise more accurate because I check
everything on the database okay I have
access to I don't know
thousands of thousands of books ten
thousand books okay so I can check
things okay all right mmm I like to tell
stories maybe you noticed
so I was going on a plane one time and
to hear a teaching by a llama and there
were lots of people on the plane that I
didn't know who we're going to this
small town to hear this person and I was
translating avi Dharma in that period I
spent 12 years translating of a dog and
so I was working on abhidharma and I
just reached the part where Buddha said
the lengthy four alcohols and and and
Buddha said well I'll tell you the story
so a Tibetan sat down next to me you
know and I didn't know him and we were
flying and he ordered a beer you know I
was kind of surprised you know and I'm
like hmm and then I had I thought a very
cool plan so I found the page where the
Buddha said don't the Buddha said if you
drink enough alcohol to put on one piece
of grass one drop
he doesn't say don't drink he says don't
call yourself a Buddhist you know don't
call yourself my student you're not my
student he says you know you're a nice
person I like you but don't call
yourself my student okay if you drink
that much alcohol so I got the page you
know and I told it to a year 2000 right
he said yeah I said can you help me out
with this page I can't get it you know
and he's like yeah and it was really
cute okay
anyway he finished a beer all right and
so that's about morality now the year 19
and 20 we do OB Dahmer okay we don't
touch IV Dharma except as it comes up in
other schools for 18 years okay year
nineteen year 20 we do I'll be Dumber
okay okay
and basically the information there
comes up in the lamrim teachings as
you've seen
and it keeps coming up in all the books
so you get a big dose of abhidharma in
the first 18 years but in year 19 and 20
you study abhidharma formally and tell
you I'll tell the truth by that time
there's normally less than 10 months
left in your class and it gets kind of
weird because you know what the other
guys know and you know what they don't
know so there can't be a debate that
debates are really boring because you've
been with these guys for eighteen years
already and you know this guy never
learned the for true so this guy never
learned that names of the twelve links
and you could debate and you're going to
get the same answer you got last year so
they do a cool thing in the monastery
they join two classes around this time
they join they bring the next class up
and the next class misses a year which
is unfortunate you know so we my class
mister we were the lower class and we
skipped a year we were brought up
because there was nobody to debate with
each other okay there's only five guys
left above us so we joined the two
classes we missed Chun a we missed
interpretations so I went back after my
Geshe and spent a couple of years
working on that okay but most people
don't ok so sometimes Garrison's have
hole in their knowledge because
something happened at the monastery okay
now what subject did we miss nice okay
Buddhist logic clear thinking okay
that's a considered so important it's
called nicknamed insta kita emptiness
sometimes they call it the door to
emptiness okay it's so important that
every year for three months you stopped
everything the whole monastery stops all
the regular classes stop and you go you
join in a special group and you go study
subject number topic number three you go
study the second school Sutra school
okay mainly from the book of
try to keep that I'm a guarantee I just
keep making this joke because I'm figure
you I don't want you to do it I don't
want you to embarrass me with somebody
talk about chandrakirti by the way I'd
like to announce major success last
night during the offering candy lie from
Singapore was kind enough to make a damn
good mother tofu which is tofu fried
with hot spices and luckily I got some
of it before it was mixed with the
chocolate cake and it was the best
mother forever hand and anytime you want
to come to my house in Ming module I'll
pay you
I'll borrow money from word okay and I
was amazing then after that we mixed
some of it with the chocolate cake and
I'm happy to report and then I I checked
in I took a bite I almost threw up
and I watched Stanley when he took a
bite and he I think the stuff came to
here and he's like you know and I don't
know how many of you had that experience
but it was a very valuable lesson and I
hope that after Geshe Michael is long
gone and you're teaching your grandkids
you will tell them the story about the
mob of tofu chocolate cake okay and
they'll never forget so by the way
that's a good teaching tool and you
should think about it okay you can
repeat 10 times to people that they
shouldn't mix some hippie thing with
2000 year Dharma you can keep repeating
it over and over again or you can just
make a mob with tofu chocolate cake and
force them to eat something and try to
connect that bad memory to a barracks
bad action you see I mean and it's much
more powerful people don't forget okay
so anytime you can come up with some
kind of game like that or something
interesting do it okay so that's kind of
your job as a teacher
I don't know your culture you know you
have your own and your Finland I don't
know anything about Finland except it
starts with Finn and it ends with lung
and you know you have your own food you
have your own stuff so
mix mix two things that are terrible
together and make your students eat it
and you do your own thing one day we did
a retreat in New York and we made a plan
we fed everybody a big heavy dinner with
lots of sugar and then we did the
meditation right after lunch and
everyone fell asleep and everyone was
unhappy and then we took we announced
that we did it on purpose to show them
not to eat those food before you
meditate and actually they got angry
people got angry why you did that to us
and I said I'm sorry but they didn't
forget it okay
year 21 to 25 okay you know sometimes I
say Geshe course takes 20 years
sometimes they say Kiyoshi course takes
25 years so 21 to 25 if you choose to go
for a higher density degree you are
waiting to be examined even if you don't
want to go for a higher degree you might
have to wait one or two or three years
because there's a limit on the number of
guesses allowed in each monastery in my
monastery it's 2-2 normal guesses and to
advance geishas so if there's a big
bottleneck of people they kind of wait
till someone dies and then they graduate
the other guy isn't you know so you can
wait for up to 10 years if you go for a
higher highest gear here you see because
you have to wait highest question you
have to be examined in all the
monasteries and all the sixth grade
seven great colleges of the tsongkhapa -
College of sera - colleges of dribble -
colleges of gunden and then touching
hoom-bow so these are seven great
colleges and you have to appear before
each college you know I I will appear
before senator jay college but I didn't
have to appear before all the colleges
see I mean then you get a lower guessing
so you know you're supposed to not waste
your time and that's when you might
study chunghae for example you might
work hard on master yen says book how to
interpret what did the Buddha really
mean okay and that's a that's a typical
period where you might study other
specialized subjects okay and tongue is
a very popular one there's another one
I'd like to mention called circle say
circle these are topics from topic
number four okay which is a Sangha
Maitreya okay the jewel of realizations
and in there for example he mentions the
twelve links of dependent and the Wheel
of Life in in like ten words and that's
it and so there's a custom to extract
that line out and write a whole book
about it okay
and that's circle means to extract juice
from a plant as medicine you see it's
the process of boiling boiling boiling
squeezing squeezing squeezing and you
get the juice out of the plant and then
you use it as medicine so so cool means
get the juice out of Maitreya and then
teach it separately
so there's five great circles in my
monastery in our monastery for example
you do study some mind only at that time
one of them is mind only one of them is
called Sam sook which is basically the
lion stance all the details of the lion
stance one of them is dependent
origination the twelve things one of
them is a and initial which means all
the possible combinations of the five
paths there's 20 permutations like
suppose you are Hinayana fur you get the
pen as henna and then you graduate to
Mahayana and
there's 20 that's a mind map and it has
20 parts so it's called the mind map 20
part mind map of how you can get to
enlightenment different ways okay and
what's cool is that these books were
missing in our monastery during the
Cultural Revolution they're all burned
all copies were burned and we didn't
have them we they were missing and John
Brady's project found them in Russia and
recovered them and input them and that
was the first book ever printed on a
computer in Tibetan in the world and it
was a two-volume set we have a copy in
in Sedona and I'm so proud of that it's
an amazing I mean if acip only did that
one thing for 30 years and spent 10
million dollars it's worth it and he did
a few more so anyway if you are waiting
for your guess you'd agree if there's a
bottleneck too many people in your class
didn't die then you you might pause and
do tongue a interpretation yin sir or
you might do those circles okay got it
okay and then every year in the winter
for three months you do lodging you do
school number two because it's so
important for every subject it's
necessary for other every subject and
then there was a custom in Tibet that
it's really cool every year for one
month the monastery would select the 50
best geisha candidates from different
classes the 50 best students and that's
your team that's your serum a team
debating team and they would all pack up
a backpack and a sleeping bag like a
blanket and they would hike to a
Monastery called John Rother it's a
special monastery small monastery in the
mountains and and they would debate
together for a whole month and sometimes
all day sometimes on many like once a
week or twice a week you do all night
you don't sleep you debate all night and
so that's kind of like the Olympics of
the bidding so if every year your
monastery stops for three months to
study logic two months is preparation
for the winter debates they're called
winter debate and in one month you go
out for the winter debates and the kids
who are not so good they stay in the
home monastery and they try to get
better for next year and then they can
compete to be on the team you see I mean
so it's very rare to go to one to be
selected for one or two and I went to
four okay I'm bragging why I told the
teacher I'm going I don't care whether
you select me or not he said I don't
know if you can do that I said I'm doing
it so I was like unofficial 51 and I'm
happy I did it because because then I
understood I had big breakthroughs in in
that subject so I'm sorry I learned it
and I it was extremely difficult
extremely hard because when they debate
they go very very fast and I was very
frustrated when I taught course 13 I
lost half of my students in New York
when I taught logic I lost half of the
students I had 80 I got forty forty
dropped out and it's hard it's very hard
and I decided I'm gonna you know that
something you I'm gonna I'm gonna figure
this out you know so don't be afraid
okay don't have laziness right go for
the difficult subjects this is some
carpets tradition and and I became that
one of the best okay
because I just I remember being so angry
and frustrated okay and then just do it
okay got it okay okay that's the year's
I'm sorry we're spending so long on that
Tim maybe we don't get to the class
tonight huh okay I'd like to cover a few
more courses okay
of course number five is yeah how karma
works so many guests why I what was one
of my motivations for putting that in
the xviii foundation courses what do you
think I said my as a westerner I'll give
you a clue yeah we were not brought up
listening to karma okay in China you
were yeah me right and at different
countries you have at least you have the
word karma and at least people talk
about it a little bit maybe a lot of
that talk is superstition but at least
you heard about it and but in my culture
in Western culture because I was doing
the course for Westerners mostly
Americans some Europeans some South
Americans Latin Americans but I I
thought I should put a course about
karma in here
so that you can kind of confirm the
details of karma you see in in America
when I was growing up I remember my mom
the I remember the first time I heard
the word karma and by the way and in in
those years like 1835
okay 1950s okay
it was very rare to would hear the word
karma but my mom I don't know somehow
she heard about it and I was killing
bugs in our house I was killing flies
with a newspaper and and my mom said
don't kill the flies you know and I'm
like why mom and she said bad karma
and I'm like what's bad karma and she
says it's gonna come back to you and I
said how what where where does it stay
where does it go where is it stored you
know and she's like I don't know it's
just bad comma okay
you know like mother says don't ask so
many questions
so my that's where most Americans
comment understanding stop there you
know we don't know where it goes we
don't know what about sees some people
say it's like a big boomerang it goes to
Mars and it comes back ten years later
like a satellite you know we have all
these weird ideas so I thought there are
so many weird ideas about karma in my
country in my culture I should we should
learn about it and as I mentioned I
think before I think it skater J said
should some cop a student said even the
people who live in the countries like to
bed or other places where people learn
about karma or karma has always talked
about people don't understand it they
just believe it because their mom
believed it
you see so and and by the way a bunker
if we get to the real class or money
family home he's going to talk about
that tonight
you know just blindly doing what your
parents did so you know that's kind of
one of the big reasons why I put a comma
course inside at that point because none
of the students grow up with karma and
they didn't understand the details okay
so we and I'm very proud of that course
it's how karma works it gives all the
details about karma now sources you know
I'll be Dumber courseö Stanley's text
and we use heavily his Tony Lamas
commentary but also commentary the first
dynamo
so the first Thai lama wrote a good
commentary he was a young man when Tom
Coplin was an old man so he spent only a
few years with some cop
and I put a picture of him in the deer I
don't know if it's too much to ask but
it's in the images for the 18 foundation
courses summary so it's gonna take him a
while but I like the photo it's a
painting I found a painting of him for
you when he met the day he met
tsongkhapa and he's got a funny little
mustache I'm sure he had to shave it off
the next day but okay monks are not
allowed to have moustache and beards
that specifically and anyway we are
allowed to not have hair up here but
don't let it come down here okay so I
used that a lot okay and I'll try to
find the painting for you this book by
the way is the best biography of some
copper in the world by about a thousand
percent so if you want to know more
about your own lineage read it for fun
it's not very difficult it's a cute book
it's an entertaining book okay and it's
big because it has lots of paintings in
it it's based on fifteen famous
paintings but I'm very proud of that
book it took 15 years to finish it and
if you really want to know about some
couples life then you know what I tell
people make it a coffee table book in
your living room and every time you have
company just open it there's a big
tradition in the monastery that we
opened this book on a holiday or on a
birthday so you know easter is coming up
Sunday we're supposed to hunt for eggs I
don't know why don't ask me but we can
open you could maybe this Sunday open up
this book just open up close your eyes
in and look at a sentence and it's a
message from Buddha and some copper
that's a tradition okay
all right you got it yet Tim are you
carving it say again what what again
didn't
ganden do ganden do denden pretendin
okay course number six yay
what is it yeah diamond cutter Sutra
okay
and you guys know that right this has an
interesting story behind it
and it's fun to tell you the stories of
how I wrote these courses so you do not
study the diamond cutter Sutra in a some
couple monastery you do not it's not
part of the course you know and it's a
big I think it's a big shame that they
don't study it
so almost geishas have not studied the
diamond cutter Sutra they know about it
but they haven't studied it and I think
I told you the story so I you know I
used to go to prayers I was living in a
Mongolian community I was living in a
Mongolian temple with about 15 months
and most of them were Mongolians and we
used to go to shut then shut then means
go to people's houses to their skin and
droop on the left okay
I say it's the first day then he got
shaved okay but we use his commentary to
abhidharma
okay I translate it for 12 years I
didn't publish it yet it's done and I
wrote a dictionary for abhidhamma and
that took me about 10 years okay on the
bus going to New York for hours every
day because I can't I can't have to
sleep in the monastery so anyway you go
for shop there which means you go to the
communities home you recite some prayers
and they give you lunch and monks love
it you also get a little red envelope
understand
so everyone signs up for stuff done you
know and because monks don't have any
income you know
and it was a poor community it was a
port town and so it was exciting for the
monks to get some money and to have
lunch a good lunch and we would all go
and you're supposed to recite something
so in Mongolia that diamond cutter Sutra
is very highly respected it's considered
very valuable so and I think in China
also Japan Vietnam so anyway we would
recite the diamond cutter Sutra and my
Abbot at that time was a blind high
level - a from Dibble Mongolian and he
memorized it right and then he would
take a diamond cutter Sutra with him to
the family's house and he'd say look he
loved to eat
in fact he died with a role in his mouth
I was there I was with him we were alone
he died with a role here upon check you
know yo-jong and and I he sat there like
this for like five minutes I'm like are
you ok just a lot he didn't say anything
so you can really die anywhere it was
hard to get the doughnut out of his hand
and I didn't need it ok - but uh so he
loved to eat so he said let's let's
split the scripture up everybody take
five pages and we can get to lunch
faster and I said but but it's gonna
sound weird we're all reciting different
pages he said they don't know anything
you know history we all recite different
pages and I had the sexy page you know
this cutting fingers off of this guy it
was very interesting so I thought I'd
like to read more about that and so
anyway I started studying the Sutra I
found in Russia John John's John's
project found the only great Tibetan
commentary there's only one guess who
it's by
Tony lama who you had some this morning
you had a taste of Tony Romo this
morning from Lamas family okay and he's
a great writer so we found that
commentary later we we input Camila
Sheila's commentary which is also very
long it's we're translating it's gonna
be about a thousand pages and there's a
short commentary by Vasa blunder I think
it's only thirty pages it's shorter than
the Sutra so good luck but anyway
something interesting happen my personal
Lama Ken Rinpoche here I think yeah he
got ill and the doctor said he had to
have an operation and so I spent many
hours sitting in the hospital with him
and I didn't have much else to do so I
said and I was in the middle of the ACI
course I said I'm sorry what's next you
know what do I do next and I said well
let's do diamond cutter Sutra you know
he's there he can't get out of bed he
has to answer questions and so I started
translating it in the hospital and
that's how I always remember this sutra
and then we made the course like that so
if someone asks you what's the flow you
can say either lunch or Hospital okay
those are the two or if you want to make
a good story for your students you can
say gosh la decided everyone needs
emptiness before they go too far in the
course and that's a pretty good reason
to okay so before you go too far in the
in the ACI foundation courses you should
have a good dose of emptiness
have we had a higher middle way
emptiness in the course yet yeah only
course one one-third right of course one
but not in any other course so you
haven't really had a course about
emptiness so of course it's excuse me
some I don't remember 500 yeah you're
right
there are some proofs but they're lower
Midway yeah there are and some of them
are also used by the higher Midway so
anyway yeah okay
so it's good to have a good dose of
diamond cutter okay that's the logic for
course number six okay I'm gonna try to
do two more today okay and then we'll
cover your homework and God knows if we
will do any of it we also found a
carving of Tony Lama in Russia so one of
the things that most of you may not know
is that Jon's team spent 14 years in the
st. Petersburg library of the Russian
Academy of Sciences okay
oriental division they spent 14 years
and they just made a catalog they didn't
input the books which we still haven't
done there and hopefully we and our
friends can get that together at least
to scan them and they have a lot of
books from dan Hong we have to try to
say that in case there's a fire there
something Russians love to smoke
understand and I saw some clothes you
know tonight the Notre Dame burnt I
think today so it things happen fires
fires happen you know so anyway so we we
had we got permission to go into the
library and when we catalogued the books
we cat loved every single drawing in
every bull
okay so there's tens of thousands of
drawings our catalog you can search
there's a special search key and so we
search for Tony llama and there's one
carving in the world and it's in st.
Petersburg and you got it you have
Tim it's in your it's in the it's in
your manual okay I put it in your manual
those carvings all look the same to be
honest you know it could be a Sangha it
could be bus Abunda but anyway under the
carving it says this is Tony Lamas so I
was happy I think it might be kind of
Tony his hat looks a little Johnny okay
there you go
okay and as you know next image or you
can just scroll down as you know that
course became the diamond cutter
business book which is now sold about a
million copies and is in 35 languages
okay and I think it's interesting that
the ACI course became the book okay and
and then that kind of started DC iron
and AC I really saw okay kind of cool
mmm okay I'm gonna do two more you okay
with that
I don't care I'm just being polite
employed okay mmm what score seven but
he suffered vows
okay the vows are my buddy something I
was trying to find a painting for it
it's kind of difficult but I did you
want to scroll down Tim this is Chandra
go me okay
Chandra go me he lived around I don't
know 600 AD something like that he was
not a monk
he was again young lifetime layman vows
which many of you have and he's
responsible for a big part of the
Bodhisattva bells he recorded them he
wrote them down and also we have vowels
from Lord Buddha and other sources and
and in this course I'm sorry are asanga
shantideva Chand ago me and Buddha four
sources for the 60
ever'body suffer and I had Chinese
friends dr. Wu contacted me recently and
asked Jonathan to teach the vows to him
because not all of that transmission got
to China in that form so it's nice to
have the 46 46 64 total how many root
both 18 and 46:18 mud baths
forty-six secondary vowels many other
instruct you know many other associate
advanced commitments but there there's a
book by its own coppa called the highway
for Bodhisattvas and i used that for the
vowels
he explains each vowel in many pages he
spends many pages on each vowel and when
that collection of scriptures the most
important collection in tibet is printed
they always put that book first there
must be a reason okay so the highway for
buddy saw student college ste ste chung
shu-kun lung cheung chiu-hung LOM okay
shun la means highway for police office
okay so we used that book now again did
it the kindness of mr. John brainy
there's an incredible book called the
string of shining jewels okay string of
shining jewels it's by a gash a from
inferior monastery called Durham just
kidding okay you got to be loyal to your
own monastery but he was a titter to one
of the dioramas 10th time on my thing
and he decided to write a book of vows
it's called dumb some say Thompson dumb
still means three sets of vowels what
are they number one freedom vowels eight
kinds of freedom vows monks nuns and
lifeline laymen bells and one day vows
and then secondly the Bodhisattva vows
thirdly the tantric vows now if you
actually write down the monks vows
that's 253 paragraphs you know to
explain each
and this gaeshi
say long some room okay he he did he
decided to write a book about all three
sets of vows but he decided to make it
short and sexy okay he doesn't talk
about he doesn't blah blah blah
he just says here's the guts of the vow
hit the ball correctly completely but
shortly okay and each each one is like
three sentences are forced under this so
he he decided to cover all the vows
including tantric vows which are
hundreds of us and he wrote this cute
book an incredible book very well
written very precise about vows we
should translate it I'm just kidding
inspired I taught it here at Diamond
Mountain during this video between I
taught the Vinaya I taught the monks
vows parts of the monks vows from this
book and it's a very by the way that was
an extremely important teaching and it
was overshadowed by other events but but
that teaching was extremely important
and if you can get a recording you
should especially if you want to become
a nun or something that you should study
it it's extremely important teaching and
I was very happy with it so anyway we
found half of his book we found half the
pages and then we spent years tracking
them down Jean Smith helped us and we
looked for the pages and finally in many
countries we found all the pages found
five pages here three pages here two
pages here and we put it together and
it's finished okay so we should give
John Brady ahem yay
[Applause]
so I'm the difficult bodysurfing elves I
took Tonka's clarifications and on the
easier ones I use guess you'd say
awesome ok what school yeah higher
middle way okay buddy suffer bells are
higher middle way okay all right one
more course then we'll go to the class
hopefully on many things by the way in
the monastery on Moneypenny who means I
hope so
inshallah it's the same as inshallah
inshallah means you know what you mean
if God wills so sometimes in the
monastery or Moneypenny who means if God
wills but maybe not we'll get to your
class don't worry inshallah but every
inch comes from well related to the
Sanskrit the word wish comes from that
the pre nasal inch drops out okay anyway
here we go
of course eight it's called death in the
realms of existence it wasn't them one
of the more popular courses you know I
announced it everybody come oh gosh now
what's the next course how did I you
know and where can you go you know what
are your options
you know after you die what are the
places you can go you know someone a
friend of mine is dying tonight there
are in intensive care they are expected
to die tonight okay and it's good to
know where you might go you know it's
good to get ready and so basically this
is a very good book about how to get
ready things like that now there's an
interesting background to this when I
was doing the courses it became very
popular to translate and to study a book
called the Tibetan Book of the Dead a
Bardo to draw in Tibetan
and it's very exotic it's very sexy I
have a someone I know a friend of mine
went crazy from reading it he was
actually put in a mental asylum so he
studied it he tried to do it without a
teacher and he spent like a year in a
mental asylum so part of Toto
interestingly that book is wrong okay
the tibetan book of dead is wrong it was
not authentic
okay accurate it's missing the first
quality okay if you study the Pardo from
the abhidhamma and from other authentic
sources sutras it's nothing like that
okay so you might want to tell people
that in that book is not correct and and
we don't study it we don't use it okay
we use the RB double crochet we use
other sources okay so I thought at the
time it would be good to put out an
accurate description of what happens
during death and what happens in the
Bardo and what are your options for
where you will go okay so once you prove
future lives in course four people are
gonna think well where am I gonna go in
this future life okay again I was
operating from a Western culture that
didn't believe in future lives so first
I have to sell future life and then
people are gonna ask me well where do I
go and what's this 49 days thing what
happens then what's the spirit world
what's the Bardo okay so I decided to
write a course after you prove that
there's future and past lives to
somebody you better help them to go
there and and and interestingly you may
be interested to know a lot of this
course was inspired by my mother because
when I first went to study Buddhism in
she got cancer and she was dying and I
went to my llama I said my mom's dying
what should I do he said bring her here
we'll teach her how to die I'm like wow
okay and my mom wasn't a Buddhist and
she wasn't interested in Buddhism and I
wrote her from India you know in those
days there's no email right it's to two
or three weeks mail I used to get
letters from her a year later sometimes
Indian mail and so I wrote her I said
come you what are you what are you gonna
lose you're dying
they kicked her out of her school she
was a schoolteacher they she had a what
he called seizure in this in the class
and they said look it's freaking the
kids out you can't cut you cannot teach
go home so she's sitting at home waiting
to die you know and I wrote her I said
come what do you what are you gonna lose
you know so she came she never traveled
outside of the US and she was very ill
we drove her up to the library in in the
back of a car she was laying down and so
we put her in the class we put her you
know up in the wall against the wall and
they taught her for three months
how to die and I was so impressed I was
like that's cool that should be a course
for everybody okay so basically this
course came from my own personal
experience that I thought it was
important that people should have a
correct
you know description of what's going to
happen to you okay so I like this course
and that's all we use abhidharma
and we use ganden drupes commentary next
picture Tim I'm sorry
man manda I'm gonna change his name to
Tim Amanda yeah there we go
I also used a book called 10 mm Tim oh
say 10 mm Tim oh so the greatest book
ever written in Tibet is Lama memo which
is the long room of some copper okay big
in English it would be about a thousand
ten thousand pages okay sorry eight
thousand pages okay if we translate it
with notes and okay and you might be
interested to know he stole the name
from an earlier book okay called ten rim
Tim OH
all the words are the same except the
first word so lamrim Tim o means the
great book on the steps of the path 10
mm o meets the great book on the steps
of the teaching and some kapa stole the
name and he stole most of the material
from 10 mm Tim OH
so Tim Lynch mo is a we call proto Lamia
proto in English means primitive early
super early
Lamia Kadamba times 1000 years ago and
it's the longest book ever written by
the Columbus as a sage II can tell you
like his text by itself is maybe 10
pages and that's typical Kadampa poetry
we don't normally see a book longer than
10 or 20 pages this is the master book
of all the Kadampa okay this is a
thousand pages and it's a whole long
room it's a whole Buddhism incredible
difficult to read old 400 years before
it's on copper okay and it was missing
in the world after the Cultural
Revolution it was missing we couldn't
find it and Jane Smith helped me Jean
Jane Smith who was Jeff's boss
for many years he helped me find it and
we work together we found we found half
of a copy in Russia we found some peace
in he somehow he ended up in Indonesia
with some pieces of it and so we joined
them all together and we made a copy and
then we reprinted it in the monastery we
input it and we print it we saved the
book okay
many years later when I'm writing to
encompass biography there's a story and
so Cobb was sitting with his students
and he's saying I wish we could find a
10 mm Tim you know I wish we could find
this book that's missing because it
sounds really good you know and they
went looking for it and they found it he
found the only copy at that time 400
years after it was written and this
painting is him all excited and usually
you use a a stick many sticks a package
of incense in the monastery you don't
like one you light the whole thing like
30 pieces of incense and then when a
high Lama comes like kilo tar everyone
has a silk scarf or a flower you
understand them sin with the red
envelope over here word can give the
biggest one and you you greet a high
Lama with incense some offering and a
silk scarf this is custom so what you
see in this picture is the book is being
delivered to Tom Kaaba and he does the
Lama thing to it he's out there with
incense and a silk scarf to put on the
books you see he's treating the book
like a high Lama okay that's what's
happening in this picture okay and so I
thought it would be auspicious lucky to
put some of that book in your course
okay so I put it in in the death and the
realms of existence course so some of
the course is translated from that book
okay it's very very cool
about three years ago some high Lama
sent me a package and they said I got
this thing from Tibet you're gonna want
it this is really rare and I opened it
up if the tin rim timbal which I printed
20 years before and I'm like wow thanks
a lot you know
ok alright ok anyway that's enough
bragging it's